College Within Records UA055
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
College Within Records
1970 -- 1977
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
College Within
UA055
3.6 Linear Feet 3 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is organized in one series: Subject files.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains subject files, records, financial records, evaluations, and publications from College Within.
Biographical / Historical
The College Within was a short-lived undergraduate program founded at Tufts University in 1971. It attempted to offer an an individualized, interdisciplinary program for students who couldn't function at their best in a conventional course framework. In 1970 John Wade Professor of Modern Languages Seymour Simches' proposal to create an entity called the College Within was approved. College Within was organized in modules of five to seven students, with a faculty member and two graduate students as advisors. Students were allowed to pursue more independent work and explore areas of particular personal interest. Students had to come up with a project topic, submit biweekly reports, and had to present their research once during the semester to their entire module. The length of the papers varied, with longer projects receiving more credits at the end of the semester. College Within met with problems after only one year in existence. The program experienced a fifty percent drop in enrollment after the first year, and by April, 1972, organizers were faced with the threat of mass desertion of the faculty. Many students didn't realize the amount of work necessary to keep up with the program, and a lack of publicity kept many upperclassmen from finding out about the program at all. Also, program administrators encountered a fear of unconventional programs among students worried about finding a job out of college in a tough market. Financially, College Within developed early problems. Although the program had won a $600,000 grant from the Spaulding-Potter Fund, it could only be used if Tufts raised matching funds. Tufts never solicited donors to match the grant, and it was lost.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
- Subject Files, 1970 -- 1977; UA055.001; 3.6 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains subject files from the College Within program, including records, program and student evaluations, financial records, and publications. Some records in this series are restricted because they contain confidential student evaluations and grades. Restricted items are not individually marked, but rather need to be evaluated on a case-by-case basis.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically by title, then chronologically
  Conditions Governing Access
  75 years from the date of creation.
  - Administrative Files, Folder 1, UA055.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Files, Folder 2, UA055.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Files, Folder 3, UA055.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Files, Folder 4, UA055.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Files, Folder 5, UA055.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Files, Folder 6, UA055.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Files: Mentor Files and Correspondence, Folder 1, UA055.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Files: Mentor Files and Correspondence, Folder 2, UA055.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports and Budgets, 1974 -- 1976; UA055.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Class Lists, UA055.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - College Within, 1970; UA055.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - College Within, 1971; UA055.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - College Within, 1972; UA055.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - College Within, 1973 -- 1974; UA055.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - College Within Assessment, 1971 -- 1973; UA055.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
  - College Within Assessment of Year II, Final Draft, 1973; UA055.001.001.00016 (Box 1)
  - College Within Council Minutes, 1971 -- 1972; UA055.001.001.00017 (Box 1)
  - College Within Council Minutes, 1973 -- 1974; UA055.001.001.00018 (Box 1)
  - College Within Council, Town Meeting and Committees Structure, 1973; UA055.001.001.00019 (Box 1)
  - College Within--General Information, UA055.001.001.00020 (Box 1)
  - The College Within Newsletter, UA055.001.001.00021 (Box 1)
  - College Within--Russell Miller, UA055.001.001.00022 (Box 1)
  - College Within--Sample Posters and Publications, UA055.001.001.00023 (Box 1)
  - Commonwealth Task Force on the Open University, 1974; UA055.001.001.00024 (Box 1)
  - Confluent Education and DRICE Information, Folder 1, UA055.001.001.00025 (Box 1)
  - Confluent Education and DRICE Information, Folder 2, UA055.001.001.00026 (Box 1)
  - Confluent Education and DRICE Information, Folder 3, UA055.001.001.00027 (Box 1)
  - Confluent Education and DRICE Information, Folder 4, UA055.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1974 -- 1977; UA055.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Eleven Student Profiles, 1971 -- 1973; UA055.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - Enabling Act, 1975; UA055.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - Evaluations, 1971 -- 1973; UA055.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of the College Within, 1971 -- 1973; UA055.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of the College Within: Questionnaire, UA055.001.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of the College Within by Students, Folder 1, UA055.001.002.00008 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of the College Within by Students, Folder 2, UA055.001.002.00009 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of the College Within by Students, Folder 3, UA055.001.002.00010 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of the College Within by Students, Folder 4, UA055.001.002.00011 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of the College Within by Students, Folder 5, UA055.001.002.00012 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of the College Within by Students, Folder 6, UA055.001.002.00013 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of the College Within by Students: Self-Evaluations, Folder 1, UA055.001.002.00014 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of the College Within by Students: Self-Evaluations, Folder 2, UA055.001.002.00015 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of the College Within by Students and Administration, UA055.001.002.00016 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of Mentors, UA055.001.002.00017 (Box 2)
  - Expression of Interest--Freshmen and Transfers, Spring 1973 for Fall, UA055.001.002.00018 (Box 2)
  - Grade Sheets, 1973 -- 1977; UA055.001.002.00019 (Box 2)
  - Grade Sheets, 1975 -- 1977; UA055.001.002.00020 (Box 2)
  - History and Proposal for the College Within, 1970; UA055.001.002.00021 (Box 2)
  - Interviews and Eleven Profiles: Evaluation of the College Within, UA055.001.002.00022 (Box 2)
  - Modules, 1973 -- 1974; UA055.001.002.00023 (Box 2)
  - Press Clippings on College Within, UA055.001.002.00024 (Box 2)
  - Publications, UA055.001.002.00025 (Box 2)
  - Publications and Press Clippings, UA055.001.002.00026 (Box 2)
  - Punchcard Grade Sheets, UA055.001.002.00027 (Box 2)
  - Reports on Incomplete Grades, Grade Change Letters, 1971 -- 1974; UA055.001.002.00028 (Box 2)
  - Staff Meeting Minutes, November 9, 1972; UA055.001.002.00029 (Box 2)
  - Student Evaluations, Fall, 1971; UA055.001.002.00030 (Box 2)
  - Student Evaluations, Spring (Including Full-Year Projects), 1972; UA055.001.002.00031 (Box 2)
  - Student Evaluations, Fall, 1972; UA055.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Student Evaluations, Spring, 1973; UA055.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Student Evaluations, Fall, 1973; UA055.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Student Evaluations, Spring, 1974; UA055.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Student Evaluations, Fall, 1974; UA055.001.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - Student Evaluations, Spring, 1975; UA055.001.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - Student Evaluations, Fall, 1975; UA055.001.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - Student Evaluations, Spring, 1976; UA055.001.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - Student Evaluations, Fall, 1976; UA055.001.003.00009 (Box 3)
  - Student Evaluations, Misc. dates and formats, UA055.001.003.00010 (Box 3)
  - Student Projects, Contracts, and Evaluations, Folder 1, UA055.001.003.00011 (Box 3)
  - Student Projects, Contracts, and Evaluations, Folder 2, UA055.001.003.00012 (Box 3)
  - Student Projects, Contracts, and Evaluations, Folder 3, UA055.001.003.00013 (Box 3)
  - Student Projects, Contracts, and Evaluations, Folder 4, UA055.001.003.00014 (Box 3)
  - Student Projects, Contracts, and Evaluations, Folder 5, UA055.001.003.00015 (Box 3)
  - Student Projects, Contracts, and Evaluations, Folder 6, UA055.001.003.00016 (Box 3)
  - Student Projects, Contracts, and Evaluations, Folder 7, UA055.001.003.00017 (Box 3)